Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is פ"ב, pei beis,
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia 82. We pick up seven lines from the
bottom on פ"א עמוד ב'. pei aleph amud beis. המלוה על המשכון.
Hamaveh al hamashkon. And our learning should be in the זכות zechus
of the safety and well-being of the חיילים chayalim and חיילות chayalot
and a speedy end of the war and a speedy return of
the hostages. Okay, so we're dealing with cases about workers and also
when they're holding onto objects and what their status is in relation
to the objects that they're working on. And this משנה mishna and
then the משנה mishna continues to deal with the case about lending
money and having received collateral for that money and what liability is
there, what responsibility is there for the creditor, the one who lent
out the money, in you know, what is his responsibility vis-à-vis the
collateral that he's holding onto. So you ask me for a $1,000
loan, I lend you $1,000 but I say give me your iPhone.
Your iPhone will be collateral until you pay off your loan and
then something happens to the iPhone. What's my liability? So the תנא
קמא tana kama of the משנה mishna said that I'm a שומר
שכר, shomer sachar, that it's a, and therefore I'm liable for גניבה
ואבידה. gneiva va'aveida. I'm only exempt if there's an אונס, oness, if
there's something completely beyond my control. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, no,
you're basically a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. You don't get anything out
of this deal. You lent money and the money is at risk
and you're not going to get interest, so you're a שומר חינם.
shomer chinam. However, if you lent fruit, you know, since you lent
apples, fresh apples, and you get back fresh apples, there you do
get a benefit because if you were to be holding onto the
apples yourself, they would get more, you know, older and rotting and
so on. So there there is some benefit and you're a שומר
שכר, shomer sachar, but if it's a straight case of money, it's
a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. That position makes a lot of sense.
Why the תנא קמא tana kama considers me to be a שומר
שכר shomer sachar is unclear and that will hopefully get clarified now
in the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take a look. המלוה על המשכון
שומר שכר. Hamaveh al hamashkon shomer sachar. לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי אליעזר.
Leima masnisin d'lo k'Rabbi Eliezer. Let's say our משנה mishna is not
like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא.
braisa. המלוה חבירו על המשכון. Hamaveh chaveiro al hamashkon. Our case. I
lend you $1,000 and you give me your iPhone. ואבד המשכון. Ve'avad
hamashkon. And I lost your iPhone, I lost the collateral. ישבע ויטול
מעותיו, Yishava veyitol me'osav, דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer.
I take an oath that I wasn't negligent and I still collect
my $1,000. Basically, I'm only a שומר חינם shomer chinam on it,
and I only have to swear that I wasn't negligent, and then
I'm allowed to collect. Okay. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva אומר, omer, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, no. יכול לומר לו, Yachol lomar lo, כלום
הלויתני אלא על המשכון. klum hilvisani ela al hamashkon.
You can say to me, look, you only agreed to lend me
the money because I gave you my iPhone. אבד המשכון אבדו מעותיך.
Avad hamashkon avdu me'osecha.
If you lose the iPhone, you're going to lose, you know, your
money. If you can't give me my iPhone, I'm not going to
give you back your money. Okay, so that's רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
He doesn't say שומר שכר, shomer sachar, seems like a different type
of a dynamic is in play here. We'll talk about that in
a minute. אבל, Aval, let's just finish the ברייתא. braisa. אבל הלוהו
אלף זוז בשטר, Aval hilvehu elef zuz bishtar,
but let's say I lent you, you asked for $1,000, I say
sure, here's $1,000, but let's write it up on a document. And
we wrote it up on a document and witnesses signed it. והניח
לו משכון עליהם. Vehiniach lo mashkon aleihem. And then you also gave
me your iPhone. In that case, דברי הכל, divrei hakol, אבד המשכון
אבדו מעותיו. avad hamashkon avdu me'osav. Everybody would agree that if the
משכון mashkon was lost, the money would be considered to be lost
as well, meaning the loan, you would not have to pay up
the loan if I lost your iPhone. Okay, so now let's understand
what this debate is about and why it matters if it's with
a שטר, shtar, without a שטר. shtar. We'll explain it according to
רש"י. Rashi. We'll do the whole סוגיא sugya according to רש"י, Rashi,
then I'll mention תוספות's Tosafos position in the end. Okay, so רש"י
Rashi understands that when, that according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the
reason, fundamental reason that I took your iPhone was to make sure
that we all remember, to make sure I remembered that you owed
me the money, to make sure when I asked you for the
money, you remembered that you owed it to me, you wouldn't say
no, you never borrowed it, maybe you genuinely would have forgotten. That's
all it's doing, it's serving as a type of a זכרון דברים.
zichron devarim. You know, as a memory aid. So therefore, there's, you
know, it's just something of yours that I'm watching and I'm a
שומר חינם. shomer chinam. That's רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer position. Totally reasonable
position.
What's
רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position? רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position is no,
the reason I took your iPhone was in order to be able
to collect from it. If when I went to you and I
said where's your $1,000 and you were broke and you didn't have
the money, I could just pocket your iPhone.
So
since I took the collateral to collect from it, and that really
much fits רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva language, you know, כלום הלויתני אלא
על המשכון, klum hilvisani ela al hamashkon, you lent me on the
משכון, mashkon, then therefore, if I can't give you back your phone,
then it's considered like, you know, that went towards the payment of
your debt. I had your משכון, mashkon, I was holding that onto
it as possible payment. So if I can't give it back to
you, it's going to be credited essentially to your payment of the
debt. That's the way, that's his understanding of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
So I should point out though that that is not an idea
of a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. It's not like I'm getting benefit
and my relationship to it is that it is something that I
am watching for you. No, the reason and my liability... Towards you
is because I'm a שומר shomer *Shomer* and I received benefit, that's
not the idea at all. The idea is that the arrangement was
that it's being held for payment of the debt and therefore if
if it's lost, it's considered that it went towards the payment of
the debt. Okay? So that's a very different logic. Now of course
according to that logically even if it got destroyed באונס *be-ones* like,
you know, lightning struck it, you know even if the then nevertheless
since I was holding onto it, if I can't give it back
to you, it gets credited towards the debt. And maybe that's genuinely
the case. So that would be very different from our משנה mishnah
*Mishna* that used the model of שומר שכר shomer sachar. *Shomer Sachar*.
So
that's
what the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rabbi Eliezer* and רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva* are about. Why does it change when
there's a שטר *Shtar*? Because when there's a שטר *Shtar* then the
שטר *Shtar*, the document, the IOU is going to make sure that
I remember and you remember that there's a loan. So in that
case we would all agree that the collateral is for even רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* would agree that the collateral, the reason
I took your iPhone was so that I could collect from it.
And therefore in that case he would agree that if the iPhone
gets lost that goes towards the payment of the debt and therefore,
you know, you don't have to pay off the the debt, assuming
it was equal to the pay- equal to the debt. So that's
the po- that's the debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*. Not really about a concept
of שומר חנם shomer chinam *Shomer Chinam*, well רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer.
*Rabbi Eliezer* would have you as a שומר חנם shomer chinam, *Shomer
Chinam*, but the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* is not really
a concept of a שומר שכר shomer sachar *Shomer Sachar*, it's really
a concept of collateral is seen towards payment of the debt. All
right. But minimally it seems that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
is against our משנה mishnah *Mishna* because רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi
Eliezer* treats you as a שומר חנם shomer chinam *Shomer Chinam* and
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma* of our משנה mishnah *Mishna*
treats you as a שומר שכר shomer sachar, *Shomer Sachar*. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says... okay... אפילו תימא
*Afilu teima* to learn from the bottom, אפילו תימא רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Afilu teima Rabbi Eliezer*, no our משנה mishnah *Mishna* can even
be going according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*. ולא קשיא
*Velo kashya*, כאן שמשכנו בשעת הלוואתו b'shat halvahato, כאן שמשכנו שלא בשעת
הלוואתו *kan she-mishkeno be-sha'at halva'ato kan she-mishkeno shelo be-sha'at halva'ato*. There's also
the difference between whether it would be the loan would be at
the time of the- the collateral be taken at the time of
the loan or the collateral be taken after the loan was already
made. Collateral taken at the time of the loan, that's when רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* would say that it is there to
serve as a memory aid, but collateral taken afterwards, we don't assume
it's a memory aid. We assume it's there to be a source
of collecting the debt. Why? Because if I needed a memory aid
I would have taken it at the beginning. And also, you know,
when the debt is already existing and then I come for to
get some collateral, it's because now I'm getting anxious about whether you'll
be able to pay or not. So when it's coming later, and
we'll see this later in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* as well, it's
always considered much more in the context of collection of the
debt. So so maybe that's the issue. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
*Rabbi Eliezer* treats you as a שומר חנם shomer chinam *Shomer Chinam*
in the ברייתא braisa. *Baraita* because it was a memory aid, it
was at the time the משכון mashkon *mashkon* was given at the
time of the loan, and in our משנה mishnah, *Mishna*, that would
be a case when it was given later and it was going
towards- it would be available for collection of the debt. And that's
why our משנה mishnah *Mishna* treats the person as a שומר שכר
shomer sachar. *Shomer Sachar* and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* would
agree with that. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no. והאידי ואידי
הלווה על המשכון תניא *Ve-ha idi ve-idi helvei al ha-mashkon tanya*, you
can't say that because both the language of our משנה mishnah *Mishna*
and the language of the ברייתא braisa, *Baraita* is הלווה על המשכון
*helvei al ha-mashkon*. So it's- there's nowhere to fit in and to
claim that one is at the time of the debt and one
is later. The language sounds like it's the exact same and the
language sounds like it's at the time of the debt. Okay. So
if that's true, then רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*, who treats
you as a שומר shomer חנם *Shomer Chinam* at the time of
the debt in the ברייתא Braisai *Baraita*, would treat you as a
שומר shomer. חנם *Shomer Chinam* in the משנה mishnah's *Mishna*. So it
seems like our משנה Mishna *Mishna* is not רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
*Rabbi Eliezer*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אלא לא lo, קשיא
*ela lo kashya*, no, no, it's not difficult. We can still make
our משנה Mishna *Mishna* work with רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*.
כאן בהלווהו מעות כאן בהלווהו פירות *kan be-halve'o maot kan be-halve'o peirot*.
The difference is money or fruit. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
says you're a שומר חנם *Shomer Chinam* in the ברייתא Braisai *Baraita*
with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva*, because that was money, you
didn't get anything. In the משנה Mishna *Mishna*, the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma *Tanna Kamma* treats you as a שומר שכר shomer sachar *Shomer
Sachar* because we'll say it's a case where you lent fruit. And
lending fruit you are getting a benefit because you're lending fresh apples
and getting back fresh apples and you don't have to worry about
them rotting. So there's an obvious problem with claiming that the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma *Tanna Kamma* is talking about a case of fruit,
which is that's the distinction that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*
puts out. והא *Ve-ha* says גמרא Gemara *Gemara* מדקתני סיפא *mi-dekattani seifa*
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, אומר הלווהו מעות שומר חנם הלווהו פירות שומר
שכר shomer sachar. *Rabbi Yehuda omer helve'o maot Shomer Chinam helve'o peirot
Shomer Sachar*, מכלל דתנא קמא לא שני ליה *mi-khlal de-Tanna Kamma lo
shani lei*. But wait, the next line of the משנה mishnah. *Mishna*
is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda*. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda* says when it's money you're a שומר חנם *Shomer Chinam*, when
it's fruit you're a שומר שכר shomer sachar? *Shomer Sachar*, makes it
clear that the first position was saying that you're always a שומר
שכר shomer sachar, *Shomer Sachar*. So גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says fine. כולה
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda היא *Kulei Rabbi Yehuda hi* and no we'll
claim that even the first line is the position of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is
not- the quote of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* is not
to disagree with the first line but to clarify the first line.
וחסורי מחסרא והכי קתני *Ve-chisura me-chasra ve-hakhi kattani*, it's effectively missing words
and here's what it's really saying. הלווה על המשכון שומר שכר Shomer
Sachar. *Helvei al ha-mashkon Shomer Sachar*. If you lend money- if if
you get a collateral you're a שומר שכר Shomer Sachar. *Shomer Sachar*
on the collateral. במה דברים אמורים *Bameh devarim amurim*, when is that
true? שהלווהו פירות *she-halve'o peirot*, if you lent fruit because then you
get the benefit of getting back fresh fruit. אבל הלווהו מעות Aval
hilvehu maos, *aval halve'o maot*, but if you lent money and you
get no benefit, שומר חנם *Shomer Chinam*, then you're a שומר חנם
*Shomer Chinam*. שהלווהו פירות, if you lent fruit, because then you get
the benefit of getting back fresh fruit. אבל הלווהו מעות, but if
you lent money and you get no benefit, שומר חינם, shomer chinam,
then you're a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. שרבי יהודה אומר הלווהו מעות
שומר חינם הלווהו פירות שומר שכר, SheRabbi Yehuda omer hilvehu maos shomer
chinam hilvehu peiros shomer sachar, because that's the distinct, that's what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, teaches. Money, collateral for money, you're a שומר חינם,
shomer chinam, you got no benefit from the exchange. Collateral for fruit,
you're a שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. Okay, very, very, very much not
פשט pshat and the גמרא Gemara doesn't like it either. So the
גמרא Gemara says אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true, that our
משנה mishnah, is going like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda so קמלי מתניתין
דלא כרבי עקיבא, kam li matnisin d'lo k'Rabbi Akiva, our משנה mishnah
is not going like רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Okay, which is because,
you know, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. says that you're considered to be
a שומר שכר Shomer Sachar, or whatever you're liable, that's the רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva of the ברייתא. braita, And then our משנה mishnah
would have it be going like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who would
be, you know, who would be saying that you're effectively a שומר
חינם. shomer chinam. Now once the גמרא Gemara, is saying that why
are we trying to see if we can make it go like
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer you know, anyway, but okay. But here it
would be more, but the other point, you know, is that a
סתם משנה stam mishnah is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is a student of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva, רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda, was also but for whatever reason the גמרא Gemara does
not want to accept that our סתם משנה stam mishnah would be
going like רבי יהודה in, in, you know, in contrast to the
position of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So it doesn't like it. Anyway,
it wasn't פשט. pshat. אלא מחוורתא מתניתין דלא כרבי אליעזר. Ela michvarta
matnisin d'lo k'Rabbi Eliezer. Fine, you're right. Our משנה mishnah treats the
person as a, as a שומר שכר, Shomer Sachar, and רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer treats the person as a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, and
to try to find it to be a case that רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer, might agree to and to force that in to the
first position of the משנה, mishnah that is not פשט. pshat. The
פשט pshat is that our משנה mishna is not like רבי אליעזר.
Rabbi Eliezer Okay, so that's number one, which is clearly true. Our
משנה is שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar, That doesn't mean that our משנה
שומר שכר Shomer Sachar is the same as רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva
Again, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva speaks more about the money is there
to represent the loan. You know, maybe as way רש"י Rashi explains,
something to be collecting from the loan, and that's why you are
liable, not because of the logic of שומר שכר. Shomer Sachar. And
we're going to see that even more so in the next statement.
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says לימא, leima,
let us say בלא שוי משכון שיעור זוזי. belo shavei mashkon shiuur
zuzai. Let, let us say that the debate of the רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva let's try to understand more
deeply their debate. Let's say their debate is when the משכון mashkon,
is not worth the full value of the loan. I lend you
a thousand dollars and instead of an iPhone, you only give me
an Apple Watch, which is only worth three hundred dollars. Okay, and
that's the debate. ובדישמואל קמיפלגי. Uvedishmuel kamifligi. They're debating
the statement of שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל, D'amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel says
האי מאן דאוזיף אלפא זוזי לחבריה. Hai man d'ozif alfa zuzai l'chavrei.
If somebody lent a thousand dollars to his friend. I lend you
a thousand dollars. ואנח ליה קתא דמגלי לוויה, V'anach lei kta d'magli
lavei, and you left me a handle of, of a sickle. That
was your collateral. All right. So in that case, you would assume
that everybody is saying that that's not really to collect from, that's
what רש"י Rashi calls the case of זכרון דברים, zichron devarim, it's
just a memory aid. But let's see what שמואל Shmuel says about
it. So שמואל Shmuel says אבד קתא דמגלי אבדו אלפא זוזי. Avad
kta d'magli avdu alfa zuzai. If you lost, if the sickle, if
the handle was lost, the thousand zuz was lost. So what does
שמואל Shmuel hold? שמואל Shmuel holds even more than we were, you
know, reading in, assuming about the position of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva?
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva we said collateral is like towards payment of
the loan, and you're, and you're liable or it's considered paid if
something happens to it. שמואל Shmuel is saying
the collateral represents the loan even completely disproportionate. So if you gave
me a thousand dollars and I gave you, you know, a handle
of, a sickle handle, that sickle handle represents the thousand dollars. And
the deal is you give it back to me and you get
back your thousand dollars. Okay, so, and if it's lost, well, okay,
if you can't give me back that, that collateral, then I don't
pay you. And that is the position of, you know, that's the
position of שמואל. Shmuel.
So, sorry about the background noise. So anyway,
so
that's what שמואל Shmuel says and maybe that's the debate. So we're
talking in a case where the, we're talking in the case where
the handle was where, excuse me, where the loan was disproportionate and
that's the case where רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. would go so far
to say and consistent with what he says in the, what he
says in the ברייתא, braita you know, you gave me the loan
for this collateral, so the collateral is lost, the loan also gets
wiped away, even
disproportionate. And, and
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say
no.
רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer would say that, you know, that's just, you
don't do this whole disproportionate thing. That, and therefore if it's, and
if it is disproportionate, it's only זכרון דברים zichron devarim and you're
a שומר חינם, shomer chinam, so you're totally exempt. That's their debate.
But if it was equal to the value of the loan, then
maybe as רש"י Rashi says, maybe everybody would agree that it's there
for collection of collateral
and, and you know they would agree in that case. But they're
debating a case where it is disproportionate. Maybe that's the issue. Okay.
So the
גמרא Gemara says,
so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: No. איבעי לא שוי משכון שיעור זוזי, Ibei lo shavi mashkon
shiur zuzei, if it's not equal, in that case
דכולי עלמא לית ליה דשמואל. dechulei alma leis lei deShmuel. Everybody would
disagree with שמואל. Shmuel. Okay, everybody would say you don't do this
thing that a handle is worth the entire loan. The worst is,
the most is that it is considered for collection and it goes
towards the payment of the loan, but not that it represents the
entire loan. Okay, so that's not the debate. Everybody would agree in
that case it is not worth the entire loan. והכא דשווי שיעור
זוזי, Vehacha deshavi shiur zuzei, and here it's talking about that it
is equal to the value of the loan, וקמיפלגי בדרבי יצחק v'kamiflgi
bid'Rabbi Yitzchak and what they're debating is the position of
רבי יצחק. Rabbi Yitzchak. דאמר רבי יצחק, D'amar Rabbi Yitzchak, מניין לבעל
חוב שקונה משכון? minayin l'baal chov shekoneh mashkon? How do you know
that a creditor takes actual ownership and possession over the collateral? שנאמר,
Shene'emar, the פסוק pasuk says, ולך תהיה צדקה. ul'cha tihyeh tzedakah.
That's talking about if you go ahead and you take collateral from
a poor person, if it's a day garment you return it in
the day, if it's a night garment you return it in the
night, and it says that when you return it each day, ולך
תהיה צדקה. ul'cha tihyeh tzedakah. Now, this is going to be a
play on words between the difference between the rabbinic meaning of the
word צדקה tzedakah and the תורה's Torah meaning. The תורה's Torah meaning
of the word צדקה tzedakah is righteousness. It'll be an act of
righteousness. But rabbinically, of course, and as we use it today, it
means charity, giving a gift to the poor. So he says, אם
אינו קונה משכון צדקה מניין? im eino koneh mashkon tzedakah minayin? So
if you're just giving him back his garment, which is the collateral,
where's the צדקה? tzedakah? You didn't give a gift to the poor,
you gave back something that was his. For it to be צדקה,
tzedakah, it has to be that you take possession of the משכון,
mashkon? and then when you give it back to him, you're giving
him something of yours. Okay, now what's the significance of the idea
that a debtor takes possession of the משכון? mashkon, Well, one relevance
could be let's say I know it's חמץ chametz and it becomes
פסח. Pesach. Are you considered to be the owner? There could be
a lot of, let's say you go ahead and you use it
to marry a woman. Are you giving her an object that you
own? But for us, the relevance is this idea of paying back
of what happens if it gets destroyed. Because if the idea is
that you're watching somebody else's object, then the discussion: are you a
שומר חינם, shomer chinam, are you a שומר שכר? Shomer Sachar? But
if the discussion is that no, when he gives you this משכון,
mashkon, the iPhone, the iWatch, whatever it is, you now own it
and now you just have to give it back to him. Well,
if you own it, that's sort of like a loan, right? I
give you money, you own it, and now you have to pay
me back other money. Okay, so I give you this, you own
it, and now you either give that back to me or if
it's not around you give me something else of equal value. So
that would translate into a חיוב אונסין, chiyuv onsin, into a strict
liability if something happens because it's fully yours and if it gets
lost or destroyed, that's your loss, and now you just have to
find something to replace it to give back. So that would be
another way in which if something happens to the משכון, mashkon. you
the creditor are liable because it's not that you're a שומר on
it, but it's your object that got destroyed and you have an
obligation to give back an object. Okay, so maybe that's the debate
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי אליעזר if you say this.
This would lead to liability. And if you don't say this, then
you would just be a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. מניין לבעל חוב
שקונה משכון? Minayin l'baal chov shekoneh mashkon? שנאמר ולך תהיה צדקה. Shene'emar
ul'cha tihyeh tzedakah. אם אינו קונה משכון צדקה מניין? Im eino koneh
mashkon tzedakah minayin? If you don't own it, what would be צדקה?
tzedakah? Must be you own it. מכאן לבעל חוב שקונה משכון. Mikan
l'baal chov shekoneh mashkon. That shows you בעל חוב baal chov takes
possession of the משכון. mashkon. ותסברא? V'tisbra? Does that really make sense
that that's the debate of רבי אליעזר and רבי עקיבא? Rabbi Akiva
אימר דאמר רבי יצחק Eimar d'amar Rabbi Yitzchak במשכנו שלא בשעת הלוואתו.
bemishkono shelo b'shat halvahato. When does רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak say this
idea when you that you own it? When you take it not
at the time of the loan. Remember that was the discussion earlier.
The more, first of all, the way חז"ל Chazal understand the פסוקים
psukim here, it's talking about the time of the loan. And anyway
the, as we, so that's, I mean, that's the key point. But
in addition, as we saw before, collateral taken at the time of
loan is more taken as for payment. So therefore this idea that
you really take full possession of it and you own it, that's
only when you get it not at the time of the loan.
That's when רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak said his position. אבל משכנו בשעת
הלוואתו מי אמר? Aval mishkono b'shat halvahato mi amar? But he never,
but he never said it when it was בשעת הלוואתו, when it
was collateral given at the time of the loan, which is what
we said the case of רבי אליעזר and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
is. אלא משכנו שלא בשעת הלוואתו. Ella mishkono shelo b'shat halvahato. So
the גמרא Gemara
says, fine, you're right. When was the collateral not at the time
of the loan? דכולי עלמא אית להו דרבי יצחק. dechulei alma is
lehu d'Rabbi Yitzchak. Everybody might very well agree to רבי יצחק Rabbi
Yitzchak that you take possession. But now we're stuck. Why are we
stuck? Because we're trying to figure out what is the basis of
רבי אליעזר and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva So let's review. Okay, רבי
אליעזר says you're a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says if it gets
lost, it goes towards the debt, either because you're a שומר שכר,
Shomer Sachar, or the way the גמרא, Gemara sort of the position
the גמרא Gemara. has been laying out, more because it goes towards
payment of the debt. That's the role of the משכון. mashkon, So
we've had three ways of understanding
what their debate is about. One is, or... Two ways at least,
but the, one is that it is, well, one I should say
is the way, three ways if you count רש"י's Rashi *Rashi's* way.
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* basically explains that the basic debate is whether this
משכון mashkon *mashkon* is just there as a זכרון דברים *zichron devarim*,
as a memory aid, in which case you're a שומר *shomer*, or
whether according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. *Rabbi Akiva*, it's there as
a something for which the debt is meant to be paid off
from and therefore, if it's no longer around, it's going towards the
payment of the debt. Not based on a שומר *shomer* idea, but
based on משכון mashkon *mashkon* is seen as a payment of the
debt. So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* tried to say, maybe actually they
would all agree with that if it was equal to the value,
and maybe what they're debating is the more extreme case of שמואל
*Shmuel* when it's disproportionate. That רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* would say even
disproportionate it's equal to the value of the debt, and רבי אליעזר
*Rabbi Eliezer* would say that no, disproportionate it's זכרון דברים *zichron devarim*,
so you would have like a three-way debate, right? When it's equal
to the debt, everybody agrees it goes towards the payment, if it's
lost it gets credited towards the payment. If it's
disproportionate, then they go to opposite extremes. Then שמואל *Shmuel* and maybe
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* would say it represents the whole debt, and
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* would say, no, it's just זכרון דברים *zichron
devarim* and you're only a שומר חנם *shomer chinam*. But the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* rejects that. We're now back to the case of it's
equal to the value of the debt. Maybe they're debating this idea
of בעל חוב קונה משכון mashkon *ba'al chov koneh mashkon*, רבי יצחק
*Rabbi Yitzchak*? No, that would be an example of just, that would
only be relevant if it was not at the time of the
loan and we're talking that it is at the time of the
loan. So what are they debating now? Equal to the amount of
debt, at the time of the loan, what are they debating? So
you could go back to what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* said, which is
do you see this as זכרון דברים *zichron devarim*, as a memory
aid, or something meant to be collected from? But now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is actually going to finally go and say maybe it
really is about שומר *shomer*, not about the משכון mashkon *mashkon* as
related to the debt, but really the question of what type of
a שומר *shomer* you are. So let's take a look at now
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this: והכא במשכון בשעת הלוואתו ובשומר אבידה קמיפלגי *Vehacha bemashkon
besha'at halva'ato uveshomer aveidah kamiflugi*. They're debating the idea of somebody who
is a שומר אבידה *shomer aveidah*. The same debate about a שומר
אבידה *shomer aveidah* would apply by a שומר משכון mashkon. *shomer mashkon*.
What's the debate? What is the status? I find a lost object,
I'm waiting to find the owner to return it, and something happens
to it, am I שומר חנם *shomer chinam*? Am I שומר שכר
Shomer Sachar *shomer sachar*? What's my relationship to it? You would think
I'm a שומר חנם *shomer chinam*. I'm watching it, I'm not getting
anything in return. But this is actually a debate of רבה Rabba
*Rabbah* and רב יוסף Rav Yosef, *Rav Yosef*. דאתמר *De'itmar*: שומר אבידה
*Shomer aveidah*. רבה Rabba *Rabbah* אמר כשומר חנם *amar kishomer chinam*, you're
a שומר חנם *shomer chinam*. רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* אמר
כשומר שכר *amar kishomer sachar*, you're a שומר שכר shomer sachar *shomer
sachar*. What is the שכר *sachar*? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says שכר
מצוה Schar Mitzvah *sechar mitzvah*. Now you could read that to mean
because you get the מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of returning a lost object.
Now you could read that to mean I get points up in
heaven, so that's שכר מצוה mitzvah. *sechar mitzvah*, that's my שכר *sachar*.
But normally we don't call that like a type of a benefit
that's relevant for monetary issues, like the principle of מצות לאו ליהנות
ניתנו *mitzvos lav lehenos nitnu*. It's not considered to be הנאה *hana'ah*
and benefit if I get if I use something to do a
מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* that I'm not allowed to get benefit from. So
the real point is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* explains elsewhere, that
if I'm doing a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, the principle of עוסק במצוה
פטור מן המצוה osek b'mitzvah patur min hamitzvah *osek bamitzvah patur min
hamitzvah* kicks in. So if I'm busy taking care of the אבידה
*aveidah*, I'm airing it out, I'm bringing it into my house, I'm
exempt from other מצות *mitzvos*. So if some poor person comes up
to me and asks me for a loaf of bread, I don't
have to give it to him. So that benefit
of עוסק במצוה *osek bamitzvah* that frees me from some other responsibilities,
that would be considered the הנאה *hana'ah* that I would get, the
benefit I would get, which according to רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav
Yosef* would make me a שומר שכר shomer sachar *shomer sachar* on
the משכון mashkon *mashkon*. So that's why רבה *Rabbah* and רב יוסף
Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef* debate about a שומר אבידה *shomer aveidah*. Now
a משכון mashkon, *mashkon* for a loan is similar. Lending money is
a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, I'm risking my money, I'm not getting interest
and so on. Lending money to a poor person is a מצוה
mitzvah, *mitzvah*. So since I get that benefit of עוסק במצוה פטור
מן המצוה osek b'mitzvah patur min hamitzvah *osek bamitzvah patur min hamitzvah*
I don't have to lend out money, then I don't have to
like give a gift to the poor when they come knocking at
my door if I'm in the process of lending some other poor
person money, עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה osek b'mitzvah patur min hamitzvah?
*osek bamitzvah patur min hamitzvah*. So therefore, that is benefit and that
makes me a שומר שכר shomer sachar *shomer sachar* on the משכון
mashkon *mashkon*. That would be the position of רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*.
And רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* would say, no, we don't look at
that מצוה mitzvah? *mitzvah* idea as benefit and therefore a שומר אבידה
*shomer aveidah*, you're a שומר חנם *shomer chinam*, and the watching of
the משכון mashkon *mashkon*, you're a שומר חנם *shomer chinam*. So finally,
finally now we are getting to try to frame the debate of
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* and רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* similar to the
phrases used in our משנה *mishna*, are you a שומר חנם *shomer
chinam* or a שומר שכר shomer sachar. *shomer sachar*, not this idea
that the משכון mashkon *mashkon* represents the loan or is payment for
the loan, which is a completely different track. Okay? So this is
a better to explain the משנה *mishna*, let's see what the גמרא
*Gemara* does with it. Okay? דאתמר שומר אבידה *De'itmar shomer aveidah*, רבה
אמר כשומר חנם *Rabbah amar kishomer chinam*, רב יוסף Rav Yosef אמר
כשומר שכר *Rav Yosef amar kishomer sachar*. לימא דרב יוסף תנאי leima
d'Rav Yosef Tannai, *Leima deRav Yosef tanna'i*? Now, does this mean that
רב יוסף *Rav Yosef* is תנאי *tanna'i*? Rav Yosef has to concede
that his position is a debate of תנאים, you know, this position
of רבי אליעזר that calls you a שומר חינם, Shomer Chinam, that
seems to be by a by a משכון, mashkon by a collateral,
presumably that's what he would argue with him even in the case
of a lost object. So רב יוסף, do would you concede that
רבי אליעזר goes against you? 'Cause he treats the person who's watching
the משכון as a שומר חינם. Shomer Chinam. Now, רש"י says that
רבה has to concede that there are those against him, because, you
know, the סתמא דמשנה Stama d'Amishna says that somebody who's watching a
משכון is a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. And there's, you know, and
רבי עקיבא effectively says that the watching person watching a משכון is
a שומר שכר. shomer sachar, So but if you and if you
work it in the concept of שומרים, shomrim, that obviously is a
רב יוסף position. But does רב יוסף have to concede that רבי
אליעזר is a רבה position, רבי אליעזר who says you're a שומר
חינם? Shomer Chinam? Let's take a look. So the גמרא says like
this, רב יוסף also, לימא דרב יוסף תנאי, לא, no, you don't
have to say that. בשומר אבידה כולי עלמא אית להו דרב יוסף.
b'shomer aveida kulei alma islei d'Rav Yosef. רב יוסף would say to
you when you're dealing with a lost object, both רבי אליעזר and
רבי עקיבא would agree that you're doing a מצוה and it's a
שכר מצוה עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה Schar Mitzvah Osek b'Mitzvah patur
min hamitzvah and therefore you're considered a שומר שכר. shomer sachar So
what is the debate about a שומר somebody watching a משכון in
our משנה and in the ברייתא that רבי אליעזר, רבי עקיבא debate?
והכא במלוה צריך למשכון קמיפלגי, V'hacha b'malve tzarich l'mashkon kamiflagi, when the
lender needs to use the משכון. רש"י explains, for example, let's say
you come and ask me for $1,000, and you happen to have
a sickle, and I'm thinking about sickle 'cause we had it before,
and it's harvest time, and nobody around has a sickle and I
can't get a sickle in time and I really could use the
sickle. So therefore what I'll say is great, I'll lend you the
money and you'll give me your sickle as a משכון and then,
you know, we'll worry about the ריבית ribbis issues that, you know,
that was discussed in the previous paragraph, but somehow we address that
and practically that gets me the benefit of being able to use
a sickle when I need a
sickle. So that's what makes it a little, I'm not doing it
לשמה, lishma, I'm not doing it for the sake of a מצוה.
So that becomes then the debate of am I considered to be
עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה osek b'mitzvah patur min hamitzvah, if I'm
doing it for this ulterior reason. מר סבר מצוה קעביד שהלוהו והוי
שומר שכר. Mar savar mitzvah ka'avid she'hoveihu v'havei shomer sachar. So רבי
עקיבא would say, you know, you're still a שומר שכר, shomer sachar
who cares you've got ulterior motives, מתוך שלא לשמה בא לשמה. mitoch
shelo lishma ba lishma. Who doesn't have ulterior motives? You know, whatever,
you're still doing it, you you you are also you're still doing
a מצוה even if that wasn't your intent, even if you were
motivated otherwise. And עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה osek b'mitzvah patur min
hamitzvah and you get the benefit of not having to give money
to a poor person who comes knocking at your door 'cause you're
still doing a מצוה here, and therefore you're a שומר שכר, shomer
sachar. you gain that benefit. ומר סבר, V'mar savar, but רבי אליעזר
would hold לאו מצוה קעביד, lav mitzvah ka'avid, you're not doing a
מצוה when you lend him the money, להנאתו מתכוין, l'hana'aso miskavein, you're
doing it for your own interest. And that undermines this being considered
a מצוה, okay, which is a fascinating issue, you know, when you're
doing things for your own interest, does it undermine it being a
מצוה? I mean, do we not say עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה?
But that's what it seems. והוה שומר חינם, V'havei shomer chinam, so
since you're not getting the benefit of עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה,
you're a שומר חינם. Shomer Chinam. Now, it's a little funny because
you would say that you are getting the benefit of using a
sickle. Somehow that's not being considered, not exactly clear why. Maybe somehow
the fact that I'm putting up my money at risk, you know,
offsets the benefit that I'm getting the use of the sickle, but
it's really a very strange, you know, maybe that that that's why
I'm doing it and that's not enough to be considered a שומר
שכר, shomer sachar maybe because I have to pay for the use
of the sickle so it shouldn't be a ריבית ribbis problem. Anyway,
רש"י does not address that. So where are we? We basically have
that our משנה has a debate of are you a שומר חינם
Shomer Chinam or a שומר שכר shomer sachar by somebody who wants
a משכון, and the גמרא is basically explained, right, רבי יהודה says
you're basically a שומר חינם Shomer Chinam except in the case of
fruit. But the סתם תנא stam Tanna was that you were שומר
שכר. shomer sachar And רש"י explains or whatever the גמרא explains rather
that that's whether you get שכר מצוה because and whether the fact
that you're עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה gets you off of having
to do other stuff. Does that make you a שומר שכר? shomer
sachar Where the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would say yes and רבי
יהודה would say no, and maybe that's also the debate of, you
know, רבי אליעזר and and רבי עקיבא. That is distinct from what
the גמרא earlier tried to make the debate about or sounded a
lot like from the ברייתא itself that it had nothing to do
with being a שומר שכר, shomer sachar but the degree to which
the משכון was payment for the loan. תוספות Tosafos has a whole
different read of the סוגיא Sugya where he tries to read all
of the earlier positions to be in line with the שומר שכר
shomer sachar idea and not with the משכון as payment for the
loan idea. Okay, let's just wrap up this משנה and then we'll
whatever, I mean and then we're going to do the next one.
אבא שאול אומר מותר לאדם להשכיר משכונו של עני להיות פוחת והולך.
Abba Shaul omer mutar l'adam l'haskir mashkono shel ani l'hiyos pocheis v'holech.
A person has a permission to hire the משכון of a poor
person to be decreasing and going. אבא שאול: Abba Shaul: מותר אדם
להשכיר משכונו של עני להיות פוחת והולך. mutar adam lehaskir mashkono shel
ani lihyot poches veholech. A person has a permission to rent out
the משכון of a poor person and credit it against the poor
person's debt because ultimately he's doing a favor for the poor person
so even without permission. So אמר רב חנא בר אמי אמר שמואל
הלכה כבא שאול. Amar Rav Chana bar Ami amar Shmuel halacha k'Abba
Shaul. We rule like אבא שאול. Abba Shaul.
We presume that that person, the poor person, would want him to
do that and he has the license to do that. So the
גמרא says, ואבא שאול לא אמר אלא במרה ופסל וקרדום. v'Abba Shaul
lo amar ela b'mara ufasal v'kardum. Even אבא שאול Abba Shaul only
said it by a shovel and a chiseler and a hammer. Why?
הואיל ונפיש אגרייהו וזוטר פחסייהו. ho'il v'nofish agraiyu v'zutar pachsaiyu.
Because you can rent them out for a significant amount of money
and they won't break and the wear and tear will be trivial.
So it's a high benefit to the poor person with very little
risk. But if there were more risk, you can't assume that the
poor person would be okay with this arrangement. All right, that was
the end of that משנה. New משנה, still dealing with workers working
on your objects, but as we've seen, they intersect a lot of
different considerations about what's the nature of your contract that you made
with them, what's their liability for the objects they're handling, all those
types of questions. Okay, so now we're going to deal similarly with
liability, but not that something happened that it got stolen, but an
accident they actually inadvertently broke it. המעביר חבית ממקום למקום. Hamavir chavit
mimakom l'makom. You hire some schleppers and they're moving your wine barrel
from one place to
another, ושברה, v'shavra, and they broke it. They tripped, they broke it,
it slipped from their hands. בין שומר חנם בין שומר שכר ישבע.
Bein shomer chinam bein shomer sachar yishava. So maybe, I see I
gave the example that you actually hired them to schlep it, but
the משנה is actually giving a case not of workers, but of
somebody who was given the job of watching it. Your job to
watch and to protect these barrels and at a certain point you
gotta maybe move them out of the way and put them back
in the storehouse, so that's part of the job. You were moving
them with license, but you're basically a שומר. So the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma says that whether you're a שומר חנם or a שומר
שכר shomer sachar you take an oath and you're exempt, meaning it's
enough that you swear that you weren't negligent
and that suffices, which is of course strange because if you're a
שומר שכר shomer sachar then it's not enough to not be negligent.
So דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, that's the position of רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So it's not enough to not be negligent. So
what you would have to say is more than that, is that
when it breaks it's considered to be an אונס. oness. The only
thing a שומר שכר shomer sachar is exempt from is אונס. oness.
Is that really true? You trip and it breaks, it slips from
your hands, those things are אונס? oness? That would certainly seem to
fall squarely in the liability of a שומר שכר. shomer sachar So
maybe you're not grossly negligent, but it didn't say lightning struck it.
A normal case, something broke, so that would be a normal case
that's not an אונס oness that you should be liable if you're
שומר שכר. shomer sachar So it's hard to understand why רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir allows the, allows the שומר שכר, oh I'm sorry, no
it doesn't say רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that's the גמרא. Why the
תנא קמא allows the שומר שכר to take the oath, okay? בין
שומר חנם בין שומר שכר ישבע. Bein shomer chinam bein shomer sachar
yishava. רבי אליעזר אומר זה וזה ישבע. Rabbi Eliezer omer zeh v'zeh
yishava.
I agree, that's exactly what I heard too. I also have that
tradition that both of them can take a שבועה. shvuah. ותמיהני אם
יכולין זה וזה לישבע. v'tmiani im yacholin zeh v'zeh lishava. But I'm
astounded that both of them can do it. Meaning, certainly I don't
get why the שומר שכר can do
it. If the barrel slipped and it broke or whatever, that's not
an אונס, oness, you should be liable as a שומר שכר. But
he says, but it sounds like he's saying I'm astounded that either
of them can make a שבועה. shvuah. Maybe even a שומר חנם,
maybe we should consider this to be פושע poshaya and negligent. Okay,
so the משנה agrees that both of them can take an oath,
but the question is raised whether either of them are entitled to,
certainly whether the שומר שכר is entitled to. So let's take a
look at the גמרא. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, our rabbis taught: המעביר
חבית ממקום למקום ושברה בין שומר חנם בין שומר שכר ישבע דברי
רבי מאיר. Hamavir chavit mimakom l'makom v'shavra bein shomer chinam bein shomer
sachar yishava divrei Rabbi Meir. So now we find that the תנא
קמא is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, סתם משנה רבי מאיר. stam mishnah
Rabbi Meir. Okay, so that's they both take an oath and they're
exempt, presumably it's considered אונס. oness. Why, very unclear. רבי יהודה אומר
שומר חנם ישבע ונושא שכר ישלם. Rabbi Yehuda omer shomer chinam yishava
v'nosei sachar yeshalem. רבי יהודה finally says the very logical position missing
in our משנה that it's considered to be not gross
negligence, so a שומר חנם can take an oath that he wasn't
negligent and be off the hook, but it's not considered an אונס
oness out of your control, so a שומר שכר has to pay.
רבי אליעזר אומר זה וזה ישבע ותמיהני אם יכולין זה וזה לישבע.
Rabbi Eliezer omer zeh v'zeh yishava v'tmiani im yacholin zeh v'zeh lishava.
So we identified the תנא קמא as רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, we
introduced the logical position of רבי יהודה, and now we're going to
the position of רבי אליעזר in the משנה that says I don't
get why anybody here can make a שבועה, shvuah, or certainly not
why the שומר שכר can. And now we're going to try to
figure out these positions. למימרא, L'meimra, the גמרא says, this seems to
say דסבר רבי מאיר נתקל לאו פושע הוא, d'savar Rabbi Meir nitkal
lav poshaya hu, that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds that the one
who trips is not negligent because he says a שומר חנם can
make the oath. It's actually even more, it sounds like he's saying
that the one who trips is... It slips and it falls or
whatever reason it falls when you're handling it, it sounds like he's
saying you're an אונס oness but certainly that you're not
negligent. והתניא, Vehatanya, but we know that's not the position of רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. We know רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds that somebody
who slips and it breaks is negligent. נשברה כדו ולא סילקה, Nishbera
kado velo silko,
you're walking in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and your pitcher falls from
your hand and it breaks and all the shards are there and
you did not remove it. נפלה גמלו ולא העמידה, Nafla gmalo velo
he’emido, your camel falls out and you didn't stand it back up
and then somebody trips and hurts themselves. רבי מאיר מחייב בנזקן Rabbi
Meir mechayeiv benizkan וחכמים אומרים פוטרים מדיני אדם וחייבים מדיני שמיים. vachachamim
omrim potrim midinei adam vechayavim midinei shamayim.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you're liable for if somebody got damaged
on it. It's like you made a בור, bor, you created this
hazard in רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, and as we're going to say,
you're considered to be negligent, so it's since through your negligence it
came about that you become responsible for any damages that ensue as
a result. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and the חכמים chachamim say
no, you're not negligent so you're exempt from court. Maybe you're חייב
chayav up in heaven because maybe there's a certain degree of fault,
maybe you should have done a quicker job cleaning it up, but
you are not negligent. But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir therefore you're not
strictly liable, you're not liable in court. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir though
says you are liable. וקיימא לן Vekayma lan says the גמרא and
we are of the position what we decide about this when we
discuss this whole issue in בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, the conclusion we
came to was דבנתקל פושע פליגי debiniskal poshea pligi that the debate
is if somebody who trips and something breaks is that considered to
be
negligent? Accidents don't just happen and is it like what level is
it? Is it in the גניבה ואבידה geneiva va'aveida level? Is it
in this high negligence level? And the גמרא says that we understand
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says you're liable if somebody hurts themselves
on the shards is because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds that you
are considered to be really negligent and therefore it's like you created
this hazard in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim and you're liable for it
and it's yours and you're responsible. So now רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir
position really
should
not only be
that a שומר שכר shouldn't be allowed to take a שבועה, shvua,
even a שומר חינם shomer chinam shouldn't be able to take a
שבועה shvua because you're really negligent. So why in our משנה can
you take a שבועה shvua and get off scot-free from not somebody
else being hurt by it but from the damages to the barrel?
So the גמרא says
where were we? So אמר רב אלעזר Amar Rav Elazar says רב
אלעזר, Rav Elazar, תברה, Tavrah, split it, break it in half. מי
ששנה זו לא שנה זו. Mi sheshana zo lo shana zo. You're
right. There's two different versions of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. The רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir of our ברייתא, they go at opposite extremes. The
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir of our ברייתא says when something when you
trip or when something falls out of your hands you're considered אונס
oness and even a שומר שכר is exempt, which is really extreme.
And the רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir of בבא קמא Bava Kamma that
says you're liable if it's in the public domain and somebody gets
hurt holds that you're considered negligent. You're right. Two extreme different positions
of
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay. ואתא רבי יהודה למימר Ve'asa Rabbi Yehuda
lemaymar and רבי יהודה comes and say no, שומר חינם ישבע נושא
שכר ישלם, shomer chinam yishava nosei sachar yeshalem, הכי דיני והכי דיני.
hachi dini vehachi dini.
Says no, that this is considered to be middle degree, not gross
negligence but not אונס. oness. So a שומר חינם shomer chinam like
his הלכה halacha swears that he wasn't negligent and is exempt, and
a שומר שכר because it is not an אונס oness a שומר
שכר will pay. Very reasonable position. ואתא רבי אלעזר למימר Ve'asa Rabbi
Elazar lemaymar and רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar comes along to say אין
גמרא כרבי מאיר. in gemara keRabbi Meir. You know what? It's true.
I have the tradition like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that both swear.
ומיהו תמיא אני אם יכולים זה וזה לישבע. Umihu tamia ani im
yacholim ze vaze lishava. I'm astounded that this and both of them
are able to swear. Certainly astounded that the שומר שכר is able
to swear. Okay, again this extreme position that you're an אונס oness
of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir seems to make no sense. בשלמא שומר
חינם משתבע דלא פשע בה, Bishlama shomer chinam mishtava d'lo pasha bah,
I could concede that a שומר חינם shomer chinam could take an
oath that he wasn't negligent. אלא שומר שכר אמאי משתבע? Ela shomer
sachar amai mishtava? Why should a שומר שכר take an oath? כי
לא פשע נמי שלומי בעי. Ki lo pasha nami shalumei ba'ei. Even
if he wasn't negligent he should still have to pay. It wasn't
an אונס. oness. It wasn't struck by lightning. So I don't get
why a שומר שכר gets off, which is exactly what רבי יהודה
is saying. So I have the tradition of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
but I don't understand it. ואפילו שומר חינם נמי, Ve'afilu shomer chinam
nami, and you know what? Because this is going the זה וזה.
ze vaze. I even wonder if a שומר חינם shomer chinam can
always take a שבועה. shvua. התינח במקום מדרון, Hatenach bemakom midron,
it's one thing if he's going down on an incline that there
it could break without him being negligent. שלא במקום מדרון מי מצי
משתבע דלא פשע? Shelo bemakom midron mi matzi mishtava d'lo pasha? But
if you're walking on level ground
how can you take an oath that you were not negligent? I
actually would say that נתקל פושע. niskal poshea. If somebody trips on
level ground if you ask me that's negligence. So he's saying I
have the tradition like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that both of them
can take a שבועה, shvua, but it makes no sense that a
שומר שכר can make a שבועה shvua because it's not an אונס
oness and even a שומר חינם. shomer chinam. I question whether a
lot of times he's allowed to make a שבועה. shvua. I would
think a lot of times it would be negligence. Okay, so you
have very reasonable positions that this certainly is not אונס, onus, it
might even sometimes be negligent. That's sort of the critique of רבי
אליעזר of his tradition, that's the position of רבי יהודה, and what
we really don't understand is רבי מאיר's Rebbe Meir position that you're
an אונס, onus, which also seems to go against a different רבי
מאיר Rebbe Meir position that you're a פושע, poshea, and we will
see tomorrow that the גמרא will come up with a special reason
that this case is different that helps explain this strange position of
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir that both can take a שבועה. shvua. Okay,
we will end with this.